{"tossups": [{"question": "This person succeeded Tomas Estrada Palma as Provisional Governor of Cuba, having much earlier served as Benjamin Harrison\u2019s second Solicitor General. This leader replaced Elihu Root as Secretary of War after serving an apprenticeship starting in 1901 as the first civilian U.S. Governor of the Philippines. This man shared the bench with McReynolds, Holmes, Brandeis, and Van Deventer, the last of whom he appointed, when he served as Chief Justice following his time in his highest office. For ten points, name this 24th President of the United States.", "answer": "William Howard<b> Taft</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A battleship named for this region provided naval support for the first battle of World War II, the Battle of Westerplatte. The Gastein Convention split control of this region between Prussia and Austria. Its namesake Question led to two wars named for part of this region. A canal in this region connects the Helgoland Bight with the Baltic Sea, and it was incorporated into the German Confederation after its seizure from Denmark. At the base of the Jutland peninsula is, for ten points, what northernmost modern-day German state, with capital Kiel?", "answer": "<b> Schleswig-Holstein</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "In a scandal involved with this program, Trevor Flugge, who was indicted in the Cole Inquiry, claimed to lose his hearing. This program was instituted soon after Kuwait was declared to be Iraq\u2019s 19th province. The Volcker report studied this program, noting that the Australian Wheat Board was getting the most illegal kickbacks from Saddam Hussein. For ten points, name this UN program that was supposed to give Iraqis nourishment in exchange for Iraq\u2019s chief export.", "answer": "<b> Oil-for-food</b> program", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "In his last years, this man served as syndic in what is now St. Charles County, Missouri. This man received the name \u201cBig Turtle\u201d after being captured by Blackfish, a Shawnee leader who besieged a town named for him. As part of a project intended to reach a region named Transylvania, this figure reached Ohio Falls in Louisville after passing near the border of Tennessee and Virginia through a mountain pass. For ten points, name this pioneer who helped the settlement of Kentucky by creating the Wildnerness Road through the Cumberland Gap in the Appalachians.", "answer": "Daniel<b> Boone</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man captured Witiges and his wife and deposed the short-lived Pope Silverius during his siege of Rome. This man defeated Gelimer ten miles south of Carthage in the Battle of Ad Decimum and later destroyed the Vandal kingdom at the Battle of Tricamarum. According to legend, this man was blinded and was reduced to begging for alms after he fell from favor. Along with an eunuch rival of his, Narses, this man helped to suppress a riot between the Blues and the Greens. The Nika riots were put down by, for ten points, what Byzantine general who served Justinian the Great?", "answer": "Flavius<b> Belisarius</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "The title character of this work \u201cwon the praise of Queen Elizabeth for the way she handed a bowl of rose water\u201d. In this work, the title character falls in love with Sasha in a \u201cFrost Fair\u201d on the Thames and is assisted by Nick Greene in publishing the poem<em> The Oak Tree</em>. This \u201cbiographical\u201d work is heavily inspired by the family history of Vita Sackville-West, the author\u2019s lover, as it progresses from Elizabethan era to modern times. For ten points, name this 1928 novel whose title character, a nobleman, lives for centuries without aging after changing sex, written by Virginia Woolf.", "answer": "<b> Orlando</b>, A Biography", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {"question": "Goran Goransson\u2019s improved converter for this process made it more efficient. This procedure was invented almost at the same time as its more common namesake inventor by William Kelly. Before this procedure was invented, a time-consuming process called cementation had to be used. A variation on this process that uses a basic lining to remove phosphorous was developed by Sidney Gilchrist Thomas. This process involves blowing air onto molten iron, thus removing impurities. For ten points, name this process that sharply decreased the cost of steel production.", "answer": "<b> Bessemer</b> process (accept<b> Gilchrist-Thomas</b> process before read)", "metadata": "Science - Chemistry"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s forces crushed a far larger army at the Battle of Monte Porzio, weakening the Commune of Rome. After divorcing his distant relative Adelheid of Vohburg, he gained Burgundy by marrying Beatrice I. He convinced Geza to join a campaign in which he routed Rum Seljuk at Iconium, but he died in an accident at the Saleph River, after which his body was preserved in a barrel of vinegar. For ten points, name this 12th century Holy Roman Emperor who drowned while traveling during the Third Crusade.", "answer": "<b> Frederick Barbarossa</b> (or<b> Frederick I</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A document addressed to this party\u2019s leadership was co-signed by Arthur MacManus and printed by the Daily Mail shortly before the 1924 general election. The forged Zinoviev letter was sent to, for ten points, what pro-Soviet political party in the United Kingdom?", "answer": "<b> Communist</b> Party<b> of Great Britain</b> (or<b> CPGB</b>; accept answers that indicate<b> Communist Party in Great Britain</b> or<b> England</b>, but do not accept \u201cCommunist Party of United Kingdom\u201d) <b>Second Quarter</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One leader of this country made a speech noting that \u201cMan\u2019s dearest possession is life,\u201d a quote from a Nikolai Ostrovsky novel; that speech advocating this country\u2019s independence was the \u201cMotion of Destiny\u201d speech. W.E.B. Dubois died in this nation, where aluminum smelters were powered using the Akosombo Dam. While visiting North Vietnam, this country\u2019s first post-independence leader was overthrown in 1966; that leader was Kwame Nkrumah. For ten points, name this country, once known as the Gold Coast which has its capital at Accra.", "answer": "Republic of<b> Ghana</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "The Philadelphia Spanish Flu outbreak was worsened when people flooded to Willow Grove Park to purchase these items. Al Capp created<em> Small Fry</em> in order to sell these items. Warner Brothers created a cartoon titled<em> Any [these items] Today?</em>, and a poster promoting these shows a hand clutching money wanting to purchase them in front of the Statue of Liberty\u2019s torch hand. Henry Morgenthau sold the first of its Series E to Franklin Roosevelt. Over $20 billion was generated by the sale of, for ten points, what debt securities that were sold in multiple War Loan Drives?", "answer": "<b> war bond</b>s (prompt on bonds)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This country\u2019s Shia majority launched protests that caused this country\u2019s neighbor to send GCC forces across the King Fahd Causeway; those protests opposed King Hamad of the al-Khalifa dynasty. For ten points, name this island kingdom that lies off the east coast of Saudi Arabia.", "answer": "Kingdom of<b> Bahrain</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "While trying to synthesize a drug to fight this disease, William Perkins accidentally synthesized the dye mauve. In the early 1900s, infection with this disease was used to cure syphilis via the high fever that this disease causes. Tu Youyou won the 2015 Nobel in Medicine for discovering that artemisinins can treat this disease. Thalassaemias can confer resistance to this disease, which is treated by a compound extracted from cinchona tree bark. Plasmodium parasites cause, for ten points, what disease that is transmitted by Anopheles mosquitos and treated with quinine?", "answer": "<b> malaria</b>", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Directed by Kenneth Bainbridge, this operation\u2019s handlers used the McDonald Ranch House in the Jornada del Muerto to house and assemble its components. This operation was commemorated by General J. Frederick Thorlin, who had a lava-rock obelisk erected to mark its hypocenter. This event ended up not using Jumbo, a steel containment vessel. It was probably codenamed from the poems of John Donne, and it centered on an object called the Gadget, which released the equivalent of 20 kilotons of TNT as a Fat Man-type implosion device. For ten points, name this July 16, 1945 explosive detonation at New Mexico\u2019s Alamogordo Bombing Range, the world\u2019s first atomic bomb test.", "answer": "<b> Trinity</b> test (accept<b> Alamogordo test</b> before \u201cAlamogordo;\u201d prompt on descriptive answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This leader allied with Prince Gong and Prince Chun in the Xinyou [shing-yoh] Coup to defeat Sushun and the Eight Regent Ministers. This ruler ordered Zeng Guofan [zuhn gwoh-fahn] to quell a rebellion, and helped appoint Zaitian to replace Tongzhi after he died. This figure was accused of embezzling naval funds to build a Marble Boat for the Summer Palace, and also quashed the Hundred Days\u2019 Reform while ruling on behalf of the Guangxu Emperor. This ruler was defeated by the Eight Nation Alliance after encouraging the army to support the Boxer Rebellion. For ten points, name this Dowager Empress of the Qing Dynasty.", "answer": "Dowager Empress<b> Cixi</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "George Tenet urged caution on the usage of this technology in opposition to Cofer Black. The editor of<em> Inspire</em> was selected in the Disposition Matrix for the usage of this technology. An example of this weapon that uses SAR is the RQ-1. These weapons, part of modern \u201cshock and awe\u201d strategy,possibly caused excessive blowback when they were used to kill Anwar al-Malaki. The Predator is a common example of, for ten points, what military aircraft that lack onboard pilots?", "answer": "<b> Drone</b>s (or<b> unmanned aerial vehicle</b>s,<b> UAV</b>s, or<b> Predator</b> drones until mention; prompt on aircraft or similar; do not accept airplanes)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Los Lobos claimed to have written the final song on this album, and Morris Goldberg played a penny whistle solo on its first single. The inspiration for this album was a bootleg cassette entitled<em> Gumboots</em>, on which a Joseph Shabalala-founded ensemble perfomed township jive. The appearance of groups such as Ladysmith Black Mambazo led Artists United Against Apartheid to protest this album. For ten points,\u201cYou Can Call Me Al\u201d was from what Paul Simon album, named for Elvis Presley\u2019s mansion?", "answer": "<b> Graceland</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>One character is mocked in this film with the line \u201cWell, I\u2019ve been to one world fair, a picnic, and a rodeo, and that\u2019s the stupidest thing I ever heard come over a set of earphones.\u201d A reference in this film to \u201ca pretty good weekend in Dallas\u201d was dubbed over</b> <b>with \u201cLas Vegas\u201d after the (+)</b> <b>JFK assassination, and in the original ending to this film,</b> <b>General Turgidson says \u201cour beloved president has been infamously struck down by a (*) </b>pie.\u201d The line \u201cGentlemen, you can\u2019t fight in here! This the War Room,\u201d is delivered by President Muffley in, for ten points, what 1964 Stanley Kubrick film about the Cold War?", "answer": "<b> Dr. Strangelove</b> or: How I Learned to Stop Worrying and Love the Bomb", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b>The longest remaining section of this trail is near Dodge City. Mirabeau Lamar launched an expedition named for this trail which sought to take control of it. A ferry in Arrow Rock was operated by the father of this trail, Willam Becknell. A modern (+) railroad combines the name of this trail with Burlington Northern. The Cimarron River was a rare source of water along this trail, which passed through the land of the (*) </b> Comanches and was used to transport American troops to the Mexican-American War. For ten points, name this 19th century trail to the West that terminated in New Mexico.", "answer": "<b> Santa Fe</b> Trail", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "For ten points, name this capital city that was occupied by the Nazis after the fall of Benito Mussolini.", "answer": "<b> Rome</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>Participants in this event attempted to escape the jurisdiction of the 1836 Punishment Act. The independence of a state established after this event was recognized by Britain in the Sand River Convention. Hundreds of participants in this event were killed in the</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>Weenen Massacre. In an extremely lopsided battle during this event, more than 3000</b> <b>warriors massacred by a few hundred settlers led by Andries Pretorius, who only suffered three wounded, at the Battle of Blood River. This event led to the establishment of republics like the (*) </b> Orange Free State and the Transvaal. For ten points, name this mass migration from the Cape to inland South Africa by Boer settlers.", "answer": "<b> Great Trek</b> (or<b> Groot Trek</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<em><b> Shaw v. Reno</b></em><b> stated that this technique\u2019s use on the basis of race was subject to strict scrutiny, which led to one case of it being overturned in</b><em><b> Miller v. Johnson</b></em><b>. One example of</b> <b>this technique was named for Governor Gustavus (+)</b> <b>Henry, who used it against future</b> <b>president Andrew Johnson. Cracking, packing, and hijacking are variations of this technique. A creature shaped like a (*) </b> dragon named this process, which the governor of Massachusetts used in 1812 to benefit the Democratic-Republican party. For ten points, name this process in which a political party changes the shape of electoral districts to benefit itself.", "answer": "<b> gerrymandering</b> (accept<b> Henry-mandering</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This man revived a land allotment method in which the center of a nine-plot arrangement of land was worked for the landowner while the outer sections were worked for the benefit of the serfs. This leader banned land sales in addition to reinstating the aforementioned</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>well field system. This leader\u2019s dynasty was essentially doomed after Liu Xiu\u2019s [lee-oo</b> <b>she-oo\u2019s] agrarian rebels won at the Battle of Kunyang; a few months later, this man was killed in his palace at (*) </b> Chang\u2019an. The Red Eyebrows rebellion targeted, for ten points, what Chinese leader who briefly interrupted the Han dynasty in 9 AD with the founding of the Xin [SHIN] dynasty?", "answer": "<b> Wang Mang</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>During the Crimean War, this man was commissioned to build the Renkioi Hospital, which had a patient death rate many times lower than other army hospitals. This man used new screw propeller technology to (+) design the first iron steamship to cross the Atlantic, the SS</b><em><b> Great Britain</b></em><b>. This man\u2019s 7-foot broad gauge competed with the narrower standard gauge to control as much (*) </b> railroad line as possible, leading to the Gauge Wars. For ten points, name this chief engineer of the Great Western Railway, named by the BBC as one of 100 Greatest Britons in 2002.", "answer": "Isambard Kingdom<b> Brunel</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}